hether hang is a scientist educator and
author in 2017 she resigned from her
tenured professorship at the Evergreen
State College where for 15 years she
provided undergraduates an evolutionary
toolkit with which to understand what it
is to be human and have to be critical
engaged citizens of the world she is an
insightful commentator about postmodern
trends within the Academy I'm grateful
to be here today I was asked to consider
ways that faculty administrators and
students might foster free expression in
higher education as such my comments are
going to be a little bit different I'm
going to offer advice for members of
each of those three groups but first
I'll say this individuals doing the
right thing cannot solve this problem
game theory tells us that as an
individual if you stand against a mob
you will be torn apart unless one of two
things are true one a large number of
other people are willing to stand with
you and quickly or to your institution
has your back most people will not stand
up for what they believe because risk
aversion and fear are powerful
motivators given this if you do stand up
you nearly guarantee that you will be
alone or close to it
that leaves the second option your
institution must have your back
institutions of higher ed must adopt the
Chicago principles such that
administrators faculty and students know
that if they do stand up and defend
their right to free expression their
institution will not turn on them the
chicago principles are probably familiar
to everyone in this room but in summary
they guarantee quote all members of the
university community the broadest
possible latitude to speak right listen
challenge and learn this begs the
question then what is a university for
as Jonathan Hyde has argued you cannot
simultaneously maximize both a pursuit
of truth and a pursuit of social justice
the University of Chicago has made it
clear that as an institution it sees its
mission as the pursuit of truth compare
this with the Evergreen State College
the public liberal arts college where I
was tenured until resigning last year an
institution that was once pedagogical
experimental and allowed for a deep dive
into ideas both disc
dangerous in 2011 evergreen modified its
mission statement to read in part
evergreen supports and benefits from a
local and global commitment to social
justice this seems innocuous on its face
not only that it seems morally good and
therefore that anyone objecting to it
must be somehow on the wrong side of
issues that us good people care about
this is in fact where the danger lies
the search for truth and beauty in its
many forms is what higher education is
for and about the Enlightenment opened
up our world and gave us among other
things the beginning of a formalization
of the scientific method one of the
great strengths of the scientific method
is its ability to reduce the role of
bias and emotion and what we understand
to be true it is at its core the
scientific method is at its core a
method for reducing bias but in an era
of information overload when it seems
that nothing can be trusted
many are reverting to feelings to
trusting their own feelings above all
else it is ironic that as people have
come to lose faith in our system they
have run from science rather than
towards it for while scientists
themselves are humans and therefore
fallible rigorous application of the
scientific method is the best cure for
human fallibility ever devised one key
distinction between humans and non-human
animals is that we acquire insight
cumulatively not only do we stand on the
shoulders of giants but riding on the
shoulders of giants is kind of our niche
we should learn from them when we can
and credit them always what we should
not do is trust that they're right
simply because they're famous or lauded
or because it is easier than thinking
for ourselves institutions of higher ed
are supposed to be in the business of
making assessing and communicating truth
claims and teaching others how to do the
same so in light of that my advice first
two administrators then to faculty and
finally to students missus follows once
an institution adopts the Chicago
principles administrators are free to
embrace and uphold them by among other
things creating explicit expectation
that protest is acceptable honourable
even but not if it hinders others
ability to hear convey and exchange
ideas
administrators should not allow vocal
authoritarian minorities to hold their
campus hostage and they certainly should
not collude with such vocal minorities
or to achieve their own goals we are in
effect experiencing of dearth of adults
people willing to make unpopular
decisions and stand by them when someone
throws a tantrum regardless of their age
ceding to them because it is easier in
the moment as always the wrong response
it creates larger Tantrums down the road
administrators and faculty in their role
as hiring authorities change their
campus with every hire of new faculty so
when hiring a chemist for instance hire
an actual chemist not a chemistry
educator which is code for something
else entirely
to faculty my advice is a little bit
trickier as faculty are in some ways the
most entrenched at the lock those
without tenure at risk of blowback for
politically incorrect actions or views
and those with tenure are more likely to
defend the status quo than to question
it although tenure is supposed to allow
for exactly the opposite faculty do not
model authoritarianism in your own
classrooms labs or studios do not rule
with fear or pointless workload ruling
with fear is easier perhaps an
establishing trust and allowing dissent
but it will backfire
similarly faculty do not encourage
students to respect you based on your
credentials either implicitly or
explicitly it is your ability to convey
and wrestle with ideas that is valuable
which you can and should model for the
students this is the one point of
difference I would take with Heather
McDonald from this morning this requires
risking being wrong and being willing to
return to your students with information
that is more accurate or relevant to the
question at hand you need as faculty to
be willing to make corrections to be
able to say I was wrong about X here's
why think of himself not as gatekeepers
to hallowed halls but as mentors and
fellow humans who are learning as you go
many people now use the internet for
discussion of deep resonant complex
ideas which can be fruitful but if you
do so rather than coming together in
real life with people who may disagree
you guarantee finding yourself in a silo
out of which you cannot see such echo
chambers
become so loud and self-referential that
you cannot cease to believe in the
reality that you can cease to believe in
the reality of anything outside of them
too many classrooms are not places for
engagement but rather for bland
dissemination of facts time together is
precious let us be willing to disagree
with respect and able to shift as we
take new ideas and ways of thinking on
board the revision of belief in the face
of new evidence is core to the
scientific method every one claiming a
life of the mind should be willing to do
the same change their minds when the
evidence calls for it and finally to
students I have the following advice
other truly this applies to everyone
consider the distinction between being
part of a group and being a follower
speak up in small conversations to among
friends when you know that there is
social pressure not to do so perhaps you
lack the confidence that your
convictions are apt but being silenced
and not exploring them as evidence that
something is amiss be open walk around
with positive expectation rather than a
feeling of grim defeat and more actually
diverse experiences will come your way
do not seek safe spaces be on the
lookout for microaggressions or demand
trigger warnings yes there are moments
when what you want is the familiar but
if you allow yourself to take umbrage at
that which is unfamiliar by convincing
yourself that unfamiliar is synonymous
with outrageous you will have an ever
narrower horizon embrace the idea of the
unexpected not just the unexpected
itself this will be easier to do if you
one have friends who actually think
differently from you or have different
life experiences to travel leaving
behind as many of the reminders and
comforts of home as you can so that you
actually immerse yourself in other
people's worlds and three explore the
physical world and not just the social
one the physical world provides non-game
above feedback on how well you are doing
spend time engaging with experiences and
tools such as sport or carpentry or
cooking but do not respond to emotion
and manipulation and you will learn much
about the universe remember or come to
realize that all brains are different
nearly all students at elite colleges
and many students at all institutions of
higher ed
have a particular way of being
academically academically successful
they read easily follow commands to do
homework even when it feels pointless
have at least some facility with writing
and math but there are many brilliant
people out there who do not fall into
this rubric neurological diversity
crosses all demographic lines and
finally do not let anyone tell you we
don't ask those questions here
dangerous questions exist and there are
going to be some ugly answers education
or research the twin goals of
post-secondary institutions other routes
towards understanding and ultimately
minimizing the prevalence of ugliness
and human interactions moving forward
disappearing ugly facts or silencing
those who speak about them gives those
facts power that they do not deserve so
students choose an institution that has
adopted the Chicago principles and then
learn how to shed light on the dark
corners of inquiry and of your own mind
thank you
you